<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title> 
               <hi rend="bold">THE CHARACTERS, OR THE Manners of the Age 
                  </hi> 
            </title>
            <author> BY Monsieur DE LA BRUYERE, of the <hi rend="ital">French</hi> Academy</author>
            <editor role="translator"> Made <hi rend="ital"> English </hi> by several Hands</editor>
           
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Information about the source</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
      <body>
         <p>I  Borrow’d the subject Matter of this Book from
            the  Publick,   and I now restore what it lent
            me.  Indeed having finish’d the whole Work,
            with the utmost regard  to Truth that I was
            capable of,’tis but just I should make it Restitution.
            The   World  may  here  view  the  Picture  I have
            drawn of it from Nature, and if I have hit on any
            defects,  which  it  agrees with me  to be such,  it
            may at leisure correct  them.   This is what a Man
            ought chiefly to propose to himself in Writing, tho
            he can’t always be sure  of success.   However, as
            long as Men distaste  Vice so little as they do,   we
            should  never  give over  reproaching them:   They
            would  perhaps be worse,  were  it not for censure
            and  Reproof, which makes Writing and Preaching
            of   absolute   necessity.   The  Orator  and  Writer
            can’t stifle the Joy they feel when they are applaud-
            ed,  but they ought to blush in themselves,  if they
            aim  at  nothing more  than Praise,   by   their  Dis-
            courses or Writings.  Besides, that the most certain
            and least equivocal  Approbation,  is the change of
            Manners
            
            
            
            2                                   The characters,  or
            Manners in their Readers  or Hearers :  We should
            neither write  nor  speak  but  for  Instruction ;  yet
            we may lawfully  rejoyce,  if we   at   the same time
            please those to whom weaddress, and by this means
            make the Truths we should advance,  the more insi-
            nuating, and the better receiv’d.  When any thoughts
            or reflections  slide into  a  Book, which have neither
            fire,  turn,  nor vivacity  agreeable to  the rest,   tho
            they  seem at first to be admitted for variety,  to di-
            vert  our Minds,   and render  them more  attentive
            on what is to follow,  but otherwise are not proper,
            sensible,   or accommodated to the capacity of the
            People,   ( whom  we must by  no means neglect  )
            both the Reader and the Author ought  to condemn
            ‘em.   This is one Rule:  There’s another, which my
            particular Interest obliges  me to  request  may not
            be forgot,  that is, always to have my Title in view,
            and to think,  as often as this. Book is read,   that I
            describe  the characters,   or Manners of the Age ;
            for  tho  I  frequently   take  ‘em from the court of
            France,   and Men  of  my  own  Nation,   yet they
            cannot  be  confin’d  to  any one  court  or  country,
            without losing a great deal of the compass and use-
            fulness of my Book,  and destroying the design of
            the Work,   which  is  to  paint Mankind in  general,
            as the order of the chapters,  and a certain insensi-
            ble connexion,   which the reflexions that compose
            them,  have one with another,   do  plainly demon-
            strate.   After  this  so  necessary a precaution,  the
            consequences  of which. ‘this  easie enough for any
            body to penetrate,    I must protest against  all cha-
            grin,   complaint,    malicious  Interpretation,   false
            Application and censure ;  against the insipid Rail-
            liers,  and the ill-meaning Readers.    Men ought to
            know how to Read,  and then  hold  their Tongues,
            or else to be able  to relate  what  they  have read,
            and
            
            
            
            
            Manners  of  the  Age.               3
            
            and    nothing more  or   less  than  what  they  have
            read ;   which   if   they  are  sometimes able  to  do,
            ‘this not enough,  unless they have the Will to do it.
            Without these conditions, which an exact and scru-
            pulous  Author  has a right  to require of  some Peo-
            ple,   as the  only     Recompence of  his    Labour,    I  
            question whether he ought  to continue Writing,   if
            he prefers  his   private  satisfaction  to   the publick
            Good,  and  a  Zeal  for  promoting Truth.   I confess,
            from the  year 1690,   and before the publishing the
            5th Edition,  I  was divided  between an  Impatience,
            to give my Book another Figure,   and a better Form,
            by  new   characters, and a  fear   left   some People
            should  say, Will these characters never be finisht?
            shall we never see any thing else from this  Author?
            On one side,  several   Men of  good  sense told me,
            the matter is solid,  useful, pleasant, inexhaustible ;
            live  long,  and treat  on’t   without   interruptions as
            long  as you  live :   What   can you  do  better ?  The   
            Follies  of  Mankind will every  year furnish you with
            a Volume.  While  others,  with  a  great  deal of Rea-
            son,  made me apprehend the capriciousness of the
            Multitude,  and    the   levity  of   the  People,  (  with
            whom,   however,  I  have   good  sause  to   be  con-
            tent. )   These  were always  suggesting  to me,  that
            for  these thirty years past,  few have  read with any
            other intent,  than for the sake of reading,  and that
            to amuse the World,  there ought  to be new  chap-
            ters and a new Title ;  that  this  humour  of  indiffe-
            rence had fill’d the shops,  and  stockt the Age with
            piles  of  dull and  tedious  Books,   without  stile  or
            Meaning,  Rules or Order,   contrary  to  Decency or
            Manners, written in haste,  read with precipitati on,
            and  only  read for their  Novelty.   They  added  far-
            ther,  if I could not  enlarge  a  sensible Book,   I had
            best sit still,   and do   nothing   I in  some  measure
            took
            
            
            
            
            
            4           The characters,  or
            took both their Advices,  as opposite as they seem’d
            to be,  and observ’d a medium which disagreed with
            neither.   I  did  not  scruple to  add   some  new  Re-
            marks,   to   those  which   already had  doubled  the
            bulk  of   the first Edition  of my  Book,  but that  the
            Publick   might   not  be  oblig’d  to  read   over what
            was done before,  to come at what has  been added
            since,  and that  they  might  immmediately find out
            what they  would  only  read,  I  took care to   distin-
            guish the second augmentation  by a   greater mark,
            and the first by a less,  as well to shew the progress
            of  my  characters,   as  to  guide  the Reader  in  the
            choice  he might be willing  to  make.    And  lest   he
            should be afraid that  I shou'd never have done with
            these  Additions,  I  added to  all my  exactness,  the
            sincere  promise to venture on nothing more of this
            kind    If  any   one  accuses   me  with   breaking  my
            word,   by  adding in   the  three  ensuing Editions  a
            great many  new  Remarks,  I  confess ingenuously I
            had not the  power  to suppress  'em.   He may  per-
            ceive,  by  mingling  what  was new with  what   was
            old,   without  any  mark  of distinction, I did  not so
            much  endeavour  to entertain  the  World  with  No
            velties,   as to  deliver down to Posterity,  a Book  of
            Manners,   more  pure,   regular  and   compleat.  To
            conclude,  what I have written are not design'ed for
            maxims ;   those  are  like  Laws   in  Morality,  and I
            have   neither  Genius  nor  Authority  sufficient   to
            qualifie me  for a  Legislator.    I  know well  enough,
            I have offended against the custom of writing Max-
            ims, which are deliver'd in short and concise Terms,
            like   the   manner   of    Oracles.    some of  my   Re-
            marks are  of this kind,   others are more  extended.
            We think  of  things differently, and we express 'em
            in a turn  altogether  as   different :   By a  sentence,
            an  Argument,   a Metaphor,   or some other Figure,
            a
            
            
            
            
            
            Manners  of   the  Age.                      
            
            a  Parallel,   a  simple  comparison,    by   a   story at
            length,   or  a  single Passage,   by  a  Description  or
            a  Picture,   from   whence proceeds   the length   or
            shortness  of   my   Reflections.    Those  who  write
            Maxims,  would be thought infaillible ;   on the  con-
            trary,   I  allow   any   body   to   say  of  me,  my  Re-
            marks are not  always good,  provided  he  will  him-
            self   make  better.
         </p>
      </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
