<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>La Bruyère, The Spectator, and Periodicity</title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Transcribed and encoded by</resp>
          <name>Francesca Colonnese</name>
          <name>Mara Minion</name>
          <name>Tyler Wagner</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <p>This digital edition was created as a project for Geoffrey Turnovsky's Textual Studies
          and Digital Editing course at the University of Washington in the Fall Quarter of 2019.
          The edition explores the connections between Jean de La Bruyère’s portrait of Ménalque,
          the absent-minded man,in Les Caractères and Eustace Budgell’s essay on Will Honeycombe,
          which appears in Addison and Steele’s Spectator issue number 77, originally published May
          29, 1711.</p>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct xml:id="Caractères">
          <monogr>
            <author>Jean de La Bruyère</author>
            <title>Les Caractères de Theophraste Traduit du Grec, avec Les Caractères ou Les Moeurs de Siècle</title>
            <edition>Ninth edition</edition>
            <imprint>
              <publisher>Estienne Michallet</publisher>
              <pubPlace>Paris</pubPlace>
              <date>1696</date>
            </imprint>
          </monogr>
        </biblStruct>
        <biblStruct xml:id="Spectator">
          <analytic>
            <author>Eustace Budgell</author>
          </analytic>
          <monogr>
            <title level="j">The Spectator</title>
            <editor>Joseph Addison</editor>
            <editor>Richard Steele</editor>
            <imprint>
              <biblScope>77</biblScope>
              <date>1711</date>
            </imprint>
          </monogr>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div1 type="periodical" xml:lang="en" source="#Spectator">
      <head><hi rend="allcaps">Numb. LXXVII</hi><title rend="allcaps">THE SPECTATOR.</title><figure
          type="sectionbreak">
          <figDesc>A line dividing the title of the periodical from the latin inscription below the
            title</figDesc>
        </figure>
        <foreign xml:lang="la">Non convivere licet, nec Urbe tota Quisquam est tam propè tam
          proculq; nobis. Mart. </foreign><figure type="sectionbreak">
          <figDesc>A line dividing the inscription from the date below the inscription</figDesc>
        </figure><date>Tuesday, May 29, 1711.</date><figure type="sectionbreak">
          <figDesc>A line dividing the date from the body text below the date</figDesc>
        </figure>
      </head>
      <p>My friend <ref target="#MT_B_1"><persName ref="#Honeycombe" rend="sc">Will Honeycombe</persName></ref> is one
        of those Sort of Men who are very often absent in Conversation, and what the French call
          <foreign xml:lang="fr" rend="italics">a reveur</foreign> and <foreign xml:lang="fr"
          rend="italics">a distrait</foreign>. <ref target="#MT_B_2">A little before our Club-time
          last Night, we were walking together in <placeName><hi rend="italics">Somerset</hi>
            Garden</placeName>, where <persName ref="#Honeycombe" rend="sc">WILL</persName> had picked up a small
          Pebble of so odd a make, that he said he would present it to a Friend of his, an eminent
          Virtuoso. After we had walked some time, I made a full stop with my Face towards the West,
          which <persName ref="#Honeycombe" rend="sc">WILL</persName>. knowing to be my usual Method of asking what's
          o'Clock, in an Afternoon, immediately pulled out his Watch, and told me we had seven
          Minutes good. We took a turn or two more, when, to my great Surprize I saw him squirr away
          his Watch a considerable way into the <placeName rend="italics">Thames</placeName>, and
          with great Sedateness in his Looks put up the Pebble, he had before found, in his fob. As
          I have naturally an Aversion to much Speaking, and do not love to be the Messenger of Ill
          News, especially when it comes too late to be useful, I left him to be convinced of his
          mistake in due time, and continued my Walk, reflecting on these little Absences and
          Distractions in Mankind, and resolving to make them the Subject of a future
          Speculation.</ref></p>

      <p><ref target="#MT_B_4">I was the more confirmed in my Design, when I considered that they
        were very often Blemishes in the Characters of Men of Excellent Sense;</ref> and helped to keep
          up the Reputation of that <hi rend="italics">Latin</hi> proverb, which <ref target="#F_S_6"> Mr. <persName
            rend="italics">Dryden</persName></ref> has Translated in the following Lines:</p>

      <p><quote type="translation" rend="italics"><l>Great Wit to Madness Sure is near ally'd,</l>
          <l>And thin Partitions do their Bounds divide.</l></quote></p>

      <p>My reader does, I hope, perceive, that I distinguish a man who is <hi rend="italics"
          >Absent</hi>, because he thinks of something else, from one who is <hi rend="italics"
          >Absent</hi> because he thinks of nothing at all: The latter is too Innocent a Creature to
        be taken notice of; but the Distractions of the former may, I believe, be generally
        accounted for from one of these Reasons.</p>

      <p>Either their Minds are wholly fixed on some particular Science, which is often the Case of
        Mathematicians and other Learned Men; or are wholly taken up with some violent Passion, such
        as Anger, Fear, or Love, which ties the Mind to some distant Object; or, lastly, these
        Distractions proceed from a certain Vivacity and Fickleness in a Man's Temper, which, while
        it raises up infinite Numbers of <hi rend="italics">Idea</hi>'s in the Mind, is continually
        pushing it on, without allowing it to rest on any particular Image. Nothing therefore is
        more unnatural than the <cb/> Thoughts and Conceptions of such a Man, which are seldom
        occasioned either by the Company he is in, or any of those Objects which are placed before
        him. While you fancy he is Admiring a Beautiful Woman, 'tis an even Wager that he is solving
        a Proposition in <persName rend="italics">Euclid</persName>; and while you may imagine he is
        reading the <name rend="italics">Paris Gazette</name>, 'tis far from being impossible that
        he is pulling down and rebuilding the Front of his Country-House.</p>

      <p>At the same time that I am endeavouring to expose this Weakness in others, I shall readily
        confess that I once laboured under the same Infirmity my self. The Method I took to Conquer
        it was a firm Resolution to learn something from whatever I was obliged to see or hear.
        There is a way of Thinking, if a Man can attain to it, by which he may strike somewhat out
        of any thing. I can at present observe those Starts of good Sense and Struggles of
        unimproved Reason in the Conversation of a Clown, with as much Satisfaction as the most
        shining Periods of the most finished Orator; and can make a shift to command my Attention at
        a <hi rend="italics">Puppet-Show</hi> or an <hi rend="italics">Opera</hi>, as well as at
          <title rend="italics">Hamlet</title> or <title rend="italics">Othello</title>. I always
        make one of the Company I am in; for though I say little myself, my Attention to others, and
        those Nods of Approbation which I never bestow unmerited, sufficiently show that I am among
        them. Whereas <persName ref="#Honeycombe" rend="sc">Will Honeycombe</persName>, tho' a Fellow of good Sense,
        is every Day doing and saying an hundred Things, which he afterwards confesses, with a
        well-bred Frankness, were somewhat <foreign xml:lang="fr">mal a propos</foreign>, and
        undesigned.</p>

      <p>I chanced the other Day to go into a Coffee-house, where <persName ref="#Honeycombe" rend="sc"
          >WILL.</persName> was standing in the midst of several Auditors whom he had gathered
        around him, and was giving them an Account of the Person and Character of <persName
          rend="italics">Moll Hinton</persName>. My Appearance before him just put him in mind of
        me, without making him reflect that I was actually present. So that keeping his Eyes full
        upon me, to the great Surprize of his Audience, he broke off his first Harangue, and
        proceeded thus,-—<said>Why now there's my Friend</said> (mentioning me by Name) <said>he is
          a Fellow that thinks a great deal, but never opens his Mouth; I warrant you he is now
          thrusting his short Face into some Coffee-house about '<hi rend="italics">Change</hi>. I
          was his Bail in the time of the <hi rend="italics">Popish-Plot</hi>, when he was taken up
          for a Jesuit.</said> If he had looked on me a little longer, he had certainly described me
        so particularly, without ever considering what led him into it, that the whole Company must
        necessarily have found me out; for which reason, remembering the old Proverb, <quote
          type="paraphase" rend="italics">Out of sight out of mind</quote>, I left the Room; and
        <pb/> and upon meeting him an Hour afterwards, was asked by him, with a great deal of good
        Humour, in what Part of the World I had lived, that he had not seen me these three Days.</p>

      <p><persName>Monsieur <hi rend="italics">Bruyere</hi></persName> has given us the Character of
          <hi rend="italics">an absent Man</hi>, with a great deal of Humour, which he has pushed to
        an agreeable Extravagance; with the Heads of it I shall conclude my present Paper.</p>

      <quote type="paraphrase">
        <p><ref target="#F_MK_2"> <persName ref="#Menalque" rend="italics">Menalcas</persName></ref> (says that excellent author) comes down in a
          Morning, opens his Door to go out, but shuts it again, because he perceives that he has
          his Night-cap on; and, examining himself further finds that he is but half shaved, that he
          has stuck his Sword on his right side, that his Stockings are about his Heels, and that
          his Shirt is over his Breeches. <ref target="#F_MK_1">When he is dress'd, he goes to Court, comes into the
          Drawing-room, and walking bolt upright under a branch of Candlesticks his Wigg is caught
          up by one of them, and hangs dangling in the Air.</ref> All the Courtiers fall a laughing, but
            <persName ref="#Menalque" rend="italics">Menalcas</persName> laughs louder than any of them, and looks
          about for the Person that is the Jest of the Company. Coming down to the Court-gate he
          finds a Coach, which taking for his own, he whips into it, and the Coachman drives off,
          not doubting but he carries his Master. As soon as he stops, <persName ref="#Menalque" rend="italics"
            >Menalcas</persName> throws himself out of the Coach, crosses the Court, ascends the
          Stair-case, and runs thro' all the Chambers with the greatest Familiarity, reposes himself
          on a Couch, and fancies himself at home. The Master of the House at last comes in,
            <persName ref="#Menalque" rend="italics">Menalcas</persName> rises to receive him, and desires him to
          sit down; he talks, muses, and then talks again. The Gentleman of the House is tired and
          amazed; <persName ref="#Menalque" rend="italics">Menalcas</persName> is no less so, but is every Moment in
          hopes that his impertinent Guest will at last end his tedious Visit. Night comes on, when
            <persName ref="#Menalque" rend="italics">Menalcas</persName> is hardly undeceived.</p>
        <p><ref target="#MT_B_3">When he is playing at Backgammon, he calls for a full Glass of Wine
            and Water; 'tis his turn to throw, he has the Box in one Hand, and his Glass in the
            other, and being extremely dry, and unwilling to lose Time, he swallows down both the
            Dice, and at the same time throws his Wine into the Tables. He writes a Letter, and
            flings the Sand into the Ink-bottle; he writes a second, and mistakes the Superscription
            : A Noble-man receives one of them, and upon opening it reads as follows. <hi
              rend="italics">I would have you, honest <persName>Jack</persName>, immediately on the
              Receipt of this, take in Hay enough to serve me the Winter</hi>. His farmer receives
            the other, and is amazed to see in it, <hi rend="italics">My lord, I received your
              Grace's Commands, with an intire Submission to</hi>--</ref> If he is at an
          Entertainment, you may see the Pieces of Bread continually multiplying around his Plate:
          'Tis true the rest of the Company want it, as well as their Knives and Forks, which
            <persName ref="#Menalque" rend="italics">Menalcas</persName> does not let them keep long. Sometimes in a
          Morning he puts his whole Family in a hurry, and at last goes out without being able to
          stay for his Coach or Dinner; and for that Day you may see him in every part of the Town,
          except the very Place where he had appointed to be upon a Business of Importance. You
          would often take him for every thing that he is not; for a Fellow quite Stupid, for he
          hears nothing; for a Fool, for he talks to himself, and has <cb/>
          <ref target="#MT_B_5">an hundred Grimaces and Motions with his Head, which are altogether
            involuntary; for a proud Man, for he looks full upon you, and takes no notice of your
            Saluting him: The Truth on't is, his Eyes are open, but he makes no use of them, and
            neither sees you, nor any Man, nor any thing else. He came once from his Country-house,
            and his own Footmen undertook to rob him, and succeeded; They held a Flambeau to his
            Throat, and bid him deliver his Purse; he did so, and coming home told his Friends he
            had been robbed; they desired to know the Particulars. <said>Ask my Servants</said>,
            says <persName ref="#Menalque" rend="italics">Menalcas</persName>, <said>for they were with
            me</said>.</ref></p>
      </quote>

        <div2 type="advertisements" xml:lang="en" source="#Spectator">
        <p><hi rend="sc">ADVERTISEMENTS</hi></p>

      <p>For the Benefit of <persName>Mr. Elrington</persName> and <persName>Mrs. Mills</persName>.
        At the Desire of Several Ladies of Quality By Her Majesty's Company of Comedians.</p>

      <p>At the <placeName>Theatre Royal in Drury-lane</placeName>, this present <date>Tuesday, the
        29th of May,</date> will be presented <ref target="#F_S_2">a Comedy, called, <title>The Gamester</title></ref>. 
        <ref target="#F_S_3">The part of the Gamester is to be perform'd by <persName>Mr. Mills</persName>, <gap reason="illegible"/> by
          <persName>Mr. Pack</persName>, <persName>Sir. Thm Valere</persName> by <persName>Mr.
          Bullock</persName>, <gap reason="illegible"/> Hazard by <persName>Mr. Bowen</persName>,
          <persName>Count Cog-Die</persName> by <persName>Mr. Bullock</persName>, <gap
          reason="illegible"/> <persName>Lady Wealthy</persName> by <persName>Mrs. Porter</persName>,
          <persName>Angelica</persName> by <persName>Mrs. Bradshaw</persName>, Mrs. <gap
          reason="illegible"/> -rity by <persName>Mr. Willis,</persName> Favourite by <persName>Mrs.
          Mills</persName>, Boxkeeper to the Ga<gap reason="illegible"/> Tube by <persName>Mr.
          Leigh</persName>.</ref> </p>

      <p>This Play is sold by <persName>Jacob Tenfon</persName> at <placeName>Shakespear's
          Head</placeName> over-against <placeName>Catherine Street in the Strand</placeName>.</p>

          <p><ref target="#F_S_4">The Entertainment of Musick</ref>, consisting of a Poets ca'led, The Passion of Sappho, Written
        by <persName>Mr. Harison</persName>, and <ref target="#F_S_1" type="annotation">The F <gap
            reason="illegible"/> of Alexander</ref>, Written by <persName>Mr. Dryden</persName>, as
            they are Set to Musick by <ref target="#F_S_5"><persName>Mr. Thomas Clayton</persName> (Author of <gap
          reason="illegible"/> ) </ref>will be Preformed at his <gap reason="illegible"/> in
        York-Buildings, this Day, being the 29th of <gap reason="illegible"/> , Beginning at <gap
          reason="illegible"/> in the Evening. Tickets; at 5 s. each, may be had at Mr. Charles <gap
          reason="illegible"/> the Corner of the <placeName>Bedford-Buildings</placeName>, and at
          <persName>Mr. Eliot</persName>'s <placeName>St. James's Coffee-house</placeName>. No Mony
        receiv'd, or Tickets given out at the House.</p>
      <p>This Poem is Sold by <persName>Jacob Tenfon</persName> at <placeName>Shakespear's
          Head</placeName> over-against <placeName>Catherine Street in the Strand</placeName></p>
      <p>Just Publish'd,</p>
      <p>An Account of the present State and Govenrment of the Empire of
          <placeName>Germany</placeName>: In a Letter to <persName>Thomas Foley</persName> of
          <placeName>Whitley</placeName> in <placeName>the County of Worcester</placeName>, Esq. by
          <persName>Mr. Vassor</persName>. Printed for <persName>Jacob Tenfon</persName> at
          <placeName>Shakespear's Head</placeName> over-against <placeName>Catherine Street in the
          Strand</placeName>.</p>
      <p>To be Sold, at a lower Rate than ordinary, at <placeName>the Queen's Head, joining to the
          Church Gate in Bedford Street, Covent Garden</placeName>, all Sorts of Duggers, Hair, and
        Worsted, Camlets, <gap reason="illegible"/> Duroys, Shagreens, Shalloons, Durants. Padua
        Serges, Shags, Serge de Nisms, Calamaneoes, and all other Goods fit for Mens Apparel. The
        Persons who now keep the Shop designing to have off the Trade, and the House and Shop to ne
        Lett at Michaelmas next. </p>
      <p>A convenient House to be Lett at <placeName>East-Acton in Middlesex</placeName>, four Rooms
        on a Floor, wall'd in, with Caoch-house, Stabling, Orchard, Garden, and all Conveniencies
        belonging to it, in very good Repair. Whosoever takes it may into it as soon as they please.
        Inquire at <persName>Mr. Lumley</persName>'s, or at the House, both in
          <placeName>East-Acton</placeName> aforesaid.</p>
      <p>All sorts of Silk Gowns, being in fresh Parcel of rich Brocades, Venetians, Tissues,
        Tabbies, Damasks, and Sattins, bought up the last Sale, and made into Gowns, with gentile
        and suitable Linings, to be Sold very cheap at <persName>Mrs. Attaway</persName>'s in
          <placeName>Deveroux Court in the Passage from the Temple to the Essex
          Buildings</placeName>, the lowest Price being writ upon each Gown. Note, there is a fresh
        Parcel of thread Sattin Gowns lined with thread Sattins.</p>
      <p>A most Incomparable Paste for the Hands, far exeeding anything ever yet in Print. It makes
        them Delicately white, sleeke and plump; fortifies them against the Scortching heat of the
        Fire or Sun, and Sharpness of the Wind, A Hand cannot be spiol'd but the use o' it will
        recover them. Sold only at <persName>Mr. Aller<gap reason="illegible"/> </persName>shop, over against
          <placeName>the Royal Exchanges</placeName>, at 2 s. 6 d. a pot, with directions; where
        is also sold the excellent Germans powder for the Scurvey in the Gums and Teeth which by
        only scouring them every Morning, whitens and sastens <gap reason="illegible"/> the Teeth to
        a Miracle; at 1 s. a <gap reason="illegible"/>
      </p>

      <p>
        <placeName rend="sc">LONDON</placeName>: Printed for <persName rend="italics">Sam.
          Buckley</persName>, at the <placeName rend="italics">Dolphin</placeName> in <placeName
          rend="italics">Little-Britain</placeName>; and Sold by <persName rend="italics">A.
          Baldwin</persName> in <placeName rend="italics">Warwick-Lane</placeName>, where
        Advertisements are in; as also by <persName rend="italics">Charles Lillie</persName>,
        Perfumer, at the Corner of <placeName rend="italics">Beauford-Buildings</placeName> in the
          <placeName rend="italics">Strand</placeName>. X</p>
      </div2>
      </div1>
      <div1 type="portrait" xml:lang="fr" source="#Caractères">
        <p>
          <pb n="280"/>
          <note type="original" place="foot" rend="italics">Ceci est moins un caractere particulier
            qu'un recuëil de faits de distractíons : ils ne sçauroient être en trop grand nombre
            s'ils sont agreables ; car les goûts étant differens , on a à choisir.</note>
          <ref target="#MT_B_1"><persName ref="#Menalque" rend="italics">Menalque</persName></ref> descend son escalier , ouvre sa porte pour sortir , il la referme ; il
          s’apperçoit qu’il est en bonner de nuit ; &amp; venant à mieux s’examiner , il se trouve
          rasé à moitié , il voit que son épée est mise du côté droit , que ses bas sont rabbatus
          sur ses talons , &amp; que sa chemise est pardessus ses chausses. S’il marche dans les
          places , il se sent tout d’un coup rudement frapper à l’estomac , ou au visage , il ne
          soup-çonne point ce que ce peut être jusqu’à c qu’ouvrant les yeux &amp; se réveillant ,
          il se trouves ou devant un timon de charrette , ou derriere un long ais de menuiserie
          que porte un ouvrier sur ses épaules. On l’a vû une fois heurter du front contre celui
          d’un aveugle , s’embarasser dans ses jambs , &amp; tomber avec lui chacùn de son côté à
          la renverse : il lui est arrivé plusieurs fois de se trouver tête pour tête à la
          rencontre d’un Prince &amp; sur son passage , se reconnoiter à peine , &amp; n’avoir que
          le loisir de se coller à un mur pour lui faire place. Il cherche , il broüille , il crie
          , il s’échauffe , il appelle ses valets l’un après l’autre ,
          <said rend="italics">on lui perd sous , on lui égare tout ,</said>  
          il demande ses gants qui’il a dans ses mains ; semblable à cette femme qui
          prenoit le temps de demander son masque , lors qu’elle l’avoit sur son visage. Il entre
          à l’appartement , &amp; passé sous un lustre où sa perruque s’accroche &amp; demeure
          suspenduë , tous les Courtisans regardent &amp; rient <persName ref="#Menalque">Menalque</persName> regarde aussi , &amp; rit
          plus haut que les autres , il cherche des yeux dans toute l’assemblée où est celui qui
          montre ses oreilles , &amp; à qui il manque une perruque. S'il va par la 
          
          <pb n="281"/>
          Ville , aprés avoir faire quelque chemin , il se croit égaré , il s'ément , &amp; il
          demande où il est à des passans , qui lui disent précisément le nom de sa ruë ; il entre
          ensuire dans sa maison, d'où il fort précipitamment, croiant qu'il s'est trompé. Il
          descend du Palais, &amp; trouvant au bas du grand degré un carosse qu'il prend pour le
          sien , il se met dedans ; le cocher touche , &amp; croit remener son Maître dans sa
          maison ; <persName ref="#Menalque">Menalque</persName> se jette hors de la portiere , traverse la cour , monte l'escalier,
          parcourt l'antichambre , la chambre, le cabinet , tout lui est familier , rien ne lui
          est nouveau , il s'affit , il se repose , il est chez soi ; le Maître arrive , celui ci
          se leve pour le recevoir , il le traite fort civilement , le prie de s'asseoir , &amp;
          croit faire les honneurs de sa chambre ; il parle , il réve , il reprend la parole ; le
          Maître de la maison s'ennuie , &amp; demeure étonné ; <persName ref="#Menalque">Menalque</persName> ne l'est pas moins, &amp;
          ne dir pas ce qu'il en pense ; il a affaire à un fâcheux , à un homme oisis , qui se
          retirera à la fin , il l'espere , &amp; il prend patience ; la nuit arrive qu'il est à
          peine détrompé. Une autre fois il rend visite à une femme , &amp; se persuadant bien tôt
          que c'est lui qui la reçoit , il s'établit dans son fauteüil , &amp; ne songe nullement
          à l'abandonner ; il trouve ensuite que cette Dame fait ses visites longues , il attend à
          tous momens qu'elle se leve &amp; le laisse en liberté ; mais comme cela tire en
          longueur qu'il a faim , &amp; que la nuit est déja avancée , il la prie à souper ; elle
          rit, &amp; si haut , qu'elle le réveille. Lui même se marie le matin , l'oublie le soir
          , &amp; découche la nuit de ses nôces : &amp; quelques années aprés il perd sa femme ,
          elle meurt entre ses bras, il assiste à ses obseques , &amp; le lendemain quand on lui
          vient dire qu'on a servi , il demande si sa femme est prête , &amp; si elle est avertie.
          
          <pb n="282"/> 
          C'est lui encore qui entre dans une Eglise , &amp; prenant l'aveugle
          qui est collé à la porte pour un pillier , &amp; sa tasse pour le benitier , y plonge la
          main , la porte à son front , lors qu'il entend tout d'un coup le pillier qui parle ,
          &amp; qui lui offre des oraisons : il s'avance dans la nef, il croit voir un Prié-Dieu ,
          il se jette lourdement dessus ; la machine plie , s'enfonce &amp; fait des efforts pour
          crier ; <persName ref="#Menalque">Menalque</persName> est surpris de se voir à genoux sur les jambes d'un fort petit homme ,
          appuié sur son dos , les deux bras passez sur ses épaules , &amp; ses deux mains jointes
          &amp; étenduës qui lui prennent le nez &amp; lui ferment la bouche , il se retire confus
          &amp; va s'agenoüiller ailleurs : il tire un livre pour faire sa priere , &amp; c'est sa
          pantoufle qu'il a prise pour ses heures , &amp; qu'il a mise dans sa poche avant que de
          sortir; il n'est pas hors de l'Eglise qu'un homme de livrée court aprés lui , le joint,
          lui demande en riant s'il n'a point la pantoufle de Monseigneur ; <persName ref="#Menalque">Menalque</persName> lui montre la
          sienne , &amp; lui dir ,
          <said rend="italics">Voilà tôutes les pantoufles que j'ia sur moi</said> 
          ; il se foüille neanmoins &amp; tire celle de l'Evêque de * * qu'il vient de quitter , qu'il a trouvé
          malade auprés de son feu &amp; dont avant de prendre congé de lui , il a ramassé la
          pantoufle , comme l'un de ses gants qui étoit à terre ; ainsi <persName ref="#Menalque">Menalque</persName> s'en retourne
          chez soi avec une pantoufle de moins. Il a une fois perdu au jeu tout l'argent qui est
          dans sa bourse , &amp; voulant continuer de joüer , il entre dans son cabinet , ouvre
          une armoir , y prend sa cassette , en tire ce qu'il lui plaît , etoit la remettre où il
          l'a prise ; il entend abboier dans son armoire qu'il vient de fermer, étonné de ce
          prodige il l'ouvre une seconde fois , &amp; il éclate de rire d'y voir son chien qu'il a
          serré pour sa cassette. <ref target = "MT_B_3">Il jouë trictrac,</ref> <pb n="283"/> il demande à boire , on lui en
          apporte , c'est à lui à joüer , il tient le cornet d'une main &amp; un verre de l'autre
          , &amp; comme il a une grande soif , il avale les dez &amp; presque le cornet , jette le
          verre dans le trictrac , &amp; inonde celui contre qui il joüe : &amp; dans une chambre
          où il est familier , il crache sur le lit , &amp; jette son chapeau à terre , en croiant
          faire tout le contraire. <ref target = "#MT_B_2">Il se promene sur l'eau , &amp; il demande quelle heure il est
            ; on lui presente une montre ; à peine l'a-t il reçûë , que ne songeant plus ni à
            l'heure , ni à la montre , il la jette dans la riviere , comme une chose qui
            l'embarasse.</ref> Lui-même écrit une longue lettre , met de la poudre dessus à plusieurs
          reprises , &amp; jette toujours la poudre dans l'encrier ; ce n'est pas tout , il écrit
          une seconde lettre , &amp; aprés les avoir cachetées toutes deux, il se trompe à
          l'adresse ; un Duc &amp; Pair reçoit l'une de ces deux lettres , &amp; en l'ouvrant y
          lit ces mots :
          <hi rend="italics">Maître Olivier , ne manquez si-tôt la presente reçûe , de m'envoier ma
            provision de foin ..... </hi>
          Son Fermier reçoit l'autre , il l'ouvre , &amp; se la fait lire
          , on y trouve ,
          <hi rend="italics">Monseigneur , j'ai reçû avec une soûmission aveugle les ordres qu'il a
            plû à vôtre Grandeur ..... </hi> 
          Lui-même encore écrit une lettre pendant la nuit , &amp;
          aprés l'avoir cachetée , il étient sa bougie, il ne laisse pas d'être surpris de ne voir
          <hi rend="italics">goutte</hi> , &amp; il sçait à peine comment cela est arrivé. <persName ref="#Menalque">Menalque</persName> descend l'escalier du
          <placeName>Louvre</placeName> , un autre le monte , <said rend="italics">c'est vous que je cherche </said> ; il le prend par la main , le
          fait descendre avec lui , traverse plusieurs cours , entre dans les salles en sort , il
          va , il revient sur ses pas ; il regarde enfin celui qu'il traîne aprés soi depuis un
          quart-d'heure , il est étonné que ce soit lui , il n'a rien à lui dire , il lui quitte
          la 
          
          <pb n="284"/> 
          main , &amp; tourne d'un autre côté. Souvent il vous interroge , &amp;
          il est déja bien loin de vous , quand vous songez à lui répondre ; ou bien il vous
          demande en courant comment se porte vôtre pere , &amp; comme vous lui dites qu'il est
          fort mal , il vous crie qu'il en est bien aise ; il vous trouve quelque autre fois sur
          son chemin ; il est ravi de vous rencontrer , il sort de chez vous pour vous entretenir
          d'une d'une certaine chose ; il contemple vôtre main , vous avez là , dit-il , un beau
          rubis , est-il balais ? il vous quitte &amp; continuë sa route : voilà l'affaire
          important dont il avoit à vous parler. Se trouve-t-il en campagne , il dit à quelqu'un
          qu'il le trouve heureux d'avoir pû se dérober à la Cour pendant l'automne , &amp;
          d'avoir passé dans ses terres tout le temps de <placeName>Fontainebleau</placeName> ; il tient à d'autres
          d'autres discours , puis revenant à celui-ci , vous avez eu , lui dit-il , de beaux
          jours à <placeName>Fontainebleau</placeName> , vous y avez sans doute beaucoup chassé. Il commence ensuite
          unconte qu'il oublie d'achever , il rit en lui-même , il éclate d'une chose qui lui
          passe par l'esprit , il répond à sa pensée , il chante entre ses dents , il siffle , il
          se renverse dans une chaise , il pousse un cri plaintif, il baaille , il se croit seul.
          S'il se trouve à un repas , on voit le pain se multiplier insensiblement sur son
          assiette ; il est vrai que ses voisins en manquent , aussi bien que de couteaux &amp; de
          fourchettes , dont il ne les laisse pas joüir long tems. On a inventé aux tables une
          grande cueillere pour la commodité du service ; il la prend , la plonge dans le plat ,
          l'emplit , la porte à sa bouche , &amp; il ne sort pas d'étonnement de voir répandu sur
          son linge sur ses habits le potage qu'il vient d'avaler. Il oublie de boire pendant tout
          le dîner ; ou s'il s'en souvient , &amp; qu'il 
          
          <pb n="285"/> 
          trouve que l'on lui donne
          trop de vin , il en <hi rend="italics">flaque</hi> plus de la moitié au visage de celui qui est à sa droite ; il
          boit le reste tranquillement , &amp; ne comprend pas pourquoi tout le monde éclate de
          rire, de ce qu'il a jetté à terre ce qu'on lui a versé de trop. Il est un jour retenu au
          lit pour quelque incommodité , on lui rend visite ; il y a un cercle d'hommes &amp; de
          femmes dans sa ruele qui l'entretiennent , &amp; en leur presence il souleve sa
          couverture &amp; crache dans ses draps. On le mene aux <placeName>Chartreux</placeName> , on lui fait voir un
          Cloître orné d'ouvrages , tous de la main d'un excellent Peintre ; le Religieux qui les
          lui explique , parle de <persName>saint Bruno</persName> , du Chanoine &amp; de son avanture , en fait une
          longue histoire &amp; la montre dans l'un ses tableaux : <persName ref="#Menalque">Menalque</persName> qui pendant la
          narration est hors du Cloître , &amp; bien loin au de là , y revient enfin , &amp;
          demande au Pere si c'est le Chanoine ou <persName>saint Bruno</persName> qui est damné. Il se trouve par
          hazard avec une jeune veuve , il lui parle de son désunt mari , lui demande comment il
          est mort ; cette femme à qui ce discours renouvelle ses douleurs , pleure , sanglotte ,
          &amp; ne laisse pas de reprendre tous les détails de la maladie de son époux , qu'elle
          conduit depuis la veille de sa fièvre qu'il se porroit bien , jusqu'à l'agonie.
          <said rend="italics">Madame </said> 
          , lui demande <persName ref="#Menalque">Menalque</persName> qui l'avoit apparemment écoutée avec attention , 
          <said rend="italics">n'aviez-vous que celui là ?</said>  
          Il s'avise un matin de faire tout hâter dans sa cuisine , il se leve avant le
          fruit &amp; prend congé de la compagnie ; on le voit ce jour-là en tous les endroits de
          la ville , hormis en celui où il a donné un rendez-vous précis pour cette affaire qui
          l'a empêché de dîner , &amp; l'a fait sortir à pied , de peur que son carosse ne le fist
          attendre. L'entendez-vous crier , gronder , s'emporter contre l'un 
          <pb n="286"/> 
          de les
          domestiques , il est étonné de ne le point voir , où peut il être , dit-il , que fait-il
          , qu'est-il devenu ? qu'il ne se presente plus devant moi , je le chasse dés à cette
          heure ; le valet arrive , à qui il demande fierement d'où il vient , il lui répond qu'il
          vient de l'endroit où il l'a envoié , &amp; il lui rend un fidele compte de sa
          commission. <ref target="MT_B_4">Vous le prendrez souvent pour tout ce qu'il n'est pas ; pour un stupide ,
            car il n'écoute point , &amp; il parle tout seul , il est sujet à de certaines grimaces
            &amp; à des mouvemens de tête involontaires ; pour un homme fier &amp; incivil , car
            vous salüez , &amp; il passe sans vous regarder , ou il vous regarde sans vous rendre le
            salut ; pour un inconsideré , car il parle de banqueroute au milieu d'une famille où il
            y a cette tache ; d'execution &amp; d'échaufaut devant un homme dont le pere y a monté ;
            de roture devant des roturiers qui sont riches , &amp; qui se donnent pour nobles.</ref> De
          même il a dessein d'élever auprés de soi un fils naturel sous le nom &amp; le personnage
          d'un valet ; &amp; quoi qu'il veüille le dérober à la connoissance de sa femme &amp; de
          les enfans , il lui échape de l'appeller son fils dix fois le jour : il a pris aussi la
          resolution de marier son fils à la fille d'un homme d'affaire , &amp; il ne laisse pas
          de dire de temps en temps en parlant de sa maison &amp; de ses ancêtres , que les
          <persName ref="#Menalque">Menalques</persName> ne se sont jamais mesalliez. Enfin il n'est ni present ni attentif dans une
          compagnie à ce qui fait le sujet de la conversation ; il pense , &amp; il parle tout à
          la fois , mais la chose dont il parle , est rarement celle à laquelle il pense , aussi
          ne parle-t-il gueres consequemment &amp; avec suite ; où il dit , non , souvent il faut
          dire oüi , &amp; où il dit oüi , croiez qu'il veut dire non; il a en vous répondant si
          
          <pb n="287"/> 
          juste les yeux fort ouverts , mais il ne s'en sert point , il ne
          regarde ni vous , ni personne , ni rien qui soit au monde : tout ce que vous pouvez
          tirer de lui , &amp; encore dans le tems qu'il est le plus appliqué &amp; d'un meilleur
          commerce , ce font ces mots : Oui vraiment. C'est vrai. Bon! Tout de bon ? Oui-da ! je
          pense qu'oui , Asseurément. Ah ! Ciel ! &amp; quelques autres monosillabes qui ne sont
          pas même placez à propos. Jamais aussi il n'est avec ceux avec qui il paroît être : il
          appelle serieusement son laquais Monsieur ; &amp; son ami , il l'appelle la Verdure : il
          dit Vôtre Reverence à un Prince du Sang , &amp; Vôtre Altesse à un Jesuite. Il entend la
          Messe , le Prêtre vient à un éternuer , il lui dit : Dieu vous assiste. Il se trouve
          avec un Magistrat ; cet homme grave par son caractere , venerable par son âge &amp; par
          sa dignité l'interroge sur un évenement , &amp; lui demande si cela est ainsi , <persName ref="#Menalque">Menalque</persName>
          lui répond , Oui, Mademoiselle. Il revient une fois de la campagne , las laquais en
          livrées entreprennent de le voler &amp; y réüssissent , ils descendent de son carosse ,
          lui portent un bout de flambeau sous la gorge , lui demandent la bourse , &amp; il la
          rend ; arrivé chez soi il raconte son avanture à ses amis , qui ne manquent pas de
          l'interroger sur les circonstances , &amp; il leur dit : Demandez à mes gens , ils y
          <ref target = "#MT_B_5">étoient.</ref>
        </p>   
      </div1>

    </body>
    
    <back>  
      <div type="CharacterList">
        <listPerson>
          <person xml:id="Honeycombe" role="fictional" sex="m">
            <persName>
              <surname>Honeycombe</surname>
              <forename>Will</forename>
            </persName>
          </person>
        </listPerson>
        <listPerson>
          <person xml:id="Menalque" role="fictional" sex="m">
            <persName>
              <surname xml:lang="fr">Menalque</surname>
              <surname xml:lang="en">Menalcas</surname>
            </persName>
          </person>
        </listPerson>
      </div>
      <div type="EditorialNotes">
      <note xml:id="MT_B_1" type="editorial">As the original footnote in La Bruyère's text
        acknowledges, the portrait of Menalque is less a study of a particular character than a
        collection of humourous instances of distraction. These brief and numerous sketches
        illustrate atemporal descriptions of a type of behavior, rather than particular instances of
        said behavior — descriptions in which Menalque is the only person of note. Budgell, on the
        other hand, adapts this material into a different form. Budgell uses anecdotes to describe
        particular instances of absent-minded behavior set in a specific time and place and told
        from the perspective of a present and participating narrator. In addition to cataloguing his
        friend, Will Honeycombe's, absent-minded behavior, Budgell's narrator provides a meditation
        on absent-mindedness in general. Though closely related, these two texts are making
        different use of literary forms.</note>
      <note xml:id="MT_B_2" type="editorial"> The scene when Menalque throws the watch into the
        river, written in Les Caractères as a brief behavioral sketch, is adapted by Budgell in No.
        77 of the Spectator as longer personal anecdote about Will Honeycombe seen through the
        particular perspective of his friend,the narrator. Interestingly, Budgell does not
        acknowledge that this particular portrait was almost copied from La Bruyère. Instead, at the
        end of the issue, he presents La Bruyère's study of the absent-minded man as a corrollary to
        his own work and includes a paraphrased translation of portions of the text.</note>
      <note xml:id="MT_B_3" type="editorial">In Budgell's translation of La Bruyère's portrait he
        includes a paraphrase of the Menalque backgammon sketch and the Menalque letter-writing
        sketch. However, he notably omits the sketch where Menalque throws the watch into the river,
        which originally falls between the two in Les Caractères. This omission seems intentional,
        and allows Budgell to acknowledge La Bruyère's influence, while hiding the fact that he
        almost directly copied the watch sketch from the original.</note>
      <note xml:id="MT_B_4" type="editorial"> At this point in the portrait, La Bruyère breaks from
        describing sketches of behavior to offer an apology for and explanation of the vice of
        distraction. In the Spectator, Budgell expands this into a longer meditation on the specific
        processes and inner workings of absent-mindedness.</note>
      <note xml:id="MT_B_5" type="editorial">The brevity, pace, and variety of the sketches and
        maxims in La Bruyère’s Caractères all align with the demands of periodicity and work well in
        a shorter medium intended for surface reading. Characters reference contemporary political
        figures and issues, and frequent circulation (through publishing new editions) helps to
        maintain relevance. Additionally,La Bruyère’s social and moral commentary allows for
        thematic continuity without depending on narrative. Because of this, Budgell, Addison and
        Steele find fruitful inspiration for their periodical in Les Caractères.</note>
      
      <note xml:id="F_MK_1" type="editorial"> The keys to Les Caractères not that this incident is inspired by
      a real life incident that occurred to Monsieur de Brancas at reception held by the Queen-Mother. La Bruyère's inclusion
      of this humorous anecdote, which seems the sort of thing to make the gossip rounds, would likely have made his fictionalization
      of de Brancas more transparent. This incident seems to particularly tread a thin line between the keys validating the character
      sketches as true to life and in maintianing enough readerly distance that the reader does not merely examine the portraits in 
      an effort to decode the character identities.</note>
      <note xml:id="F_MK_2" type="annotation"> Keys to the Characters decipher this person to be M. de Brancas
        
        <p n="fr">266. <hi rend="italics">Menelaque</hi>. Feu <persName>M. de Brancas</persName>, Chevalier d’honneur de la Reine-mere, 
          frere de <persName>M. le Duc de Villars</persName>. L’on conte de lui différentes fortes d’absence 
          d’esprit. L’aventure de la perruque , dont il est parlé ici, lui arriva chez la 
          Reine. L'on veut qu’il oublia le jour de ses nôces , qu’il étoit marié avec <persName>Mademoiselle Garnier</persName> , 
          fille du Partisan : &amp; que le soir, retournant chez lui à son ordinaire , 
          il sut surpris de n’y point trouver ses Valets de chambre , qu’il apprit 
          être allés mettre la toilette chez fa nouvelle femme : ce qui le fit ressouvenir de la cérémonie du matin.
          <bibl>Clef des Characteres dde La Bruyere. 1765.</bibl>
        </p>
        
        <p n="en">
          Charactères, Chap. xi. de l'Homme.<persName> La Bruyère</persName>'s 
          <persName>Menalque</persName> was identified with a <persName>M. de Brancas</persName>, 
          brother of the <persName>Duke de Villars</persName>. The adventure of the wig is said really to have happened to him 
          at a reception by the Queen-Mother. He was said also on his wedding-day to have forgotten that he 
          had been married. He went abroad as usual, and only remembered the ceremony of the moming upon 
          finding the changed state of his household when, as usual, he came home in the evening,
          <bibl>The Spectator Project: A Hypermedia Research Archive of Eighteenth-Century Periodicals. Rutgers University Libraries, 2006. http://www2.scc.rutgers.edu/spectator/complete.html.</bibl>
        </p></note>
        <note xml:id="F_S_1" type="annotation">Likely Alexander's Feast</note>
        <note xml:id="F_S_2" type="annotation"> This is a revival of Susanna Centlivre's 1705 The Gamester. Centlivre was an 
        English playwright whose comedies were often preformed at the Theatre Royal at Drury Lane, with The Gamester 
        having been preformed every year since it's premiere (Bowyer 63). 
        <bibl>Bowyer, John Wilson. The Celebrated Mrs. Centlivre. Duke University Press, 1952.</bibl> </note>
      <note xml:id="F_S_3" type="annotation"> This section of advertisment has a large quantity of smudges. However, it is 
        possible to create a more correct version by examinig the character list from Centrilivre play: 
        The part of the Gamester is to be perform'd by <persName>Mr. Mills</persName>, Hector by
        <persName>Mr. Pack</persName>, <persName>Sir. Thm Valere</persName> by <persName>Mr.
          Bullock</persName>, Marquiss of Hazard by <persName>Mr. Bowen</persName>,
        <persName>Count Cog-Die</persName> by <persName>Mr. Bullock</persName>, <gap
          reason="illegible"/> <persName>Lady Wealthy</persName> by <persName>Mrs. Porter</persName>,
        <persName>Angelica</persName> by <persName>Mrs. Bradshaw</persName>, Mrs. Security by <persName>Mr. Willis,</persName> Favourite by <persName>Mrs.
            Mills</persName>, Boxkeeper to the Ga<gap reason="illegible"/> Tube by <persName>Mr.
              Leigh</persName>.<bibl>Centlivre, Susanna. The gamester: a comedy. As it is acted at the Theatre Royal in Lincolns-Inn-Fields. 
                By His Majesty's servants. London. 1734.</bibl></note>
        <note xml:id="F_S_4" type="annotation"> This was the second of three concerts, the others taking place on May 24 and July 16,
          which had been organized at the behest of Richard Steele in which the poet John Hughes' reworking of Dryden's Alexander's Feast 
          and William Harrison's The Passion of Sappho were adapted for music by Thomas Clayton.
          <bibl>McGeary, Thomas. "Thomas Clayton and the Introduction of Italian Opera to England." Philological Quarterly, vol. 77, no. 2, 1998, p. 171.</bibl></note>
        <note xml:id="F_S_5" type="annotation"> Thomas Clayton was a minor composer of light opera in the period. 
          The illegible text likely reads, "Author of Arsinoe," his best known work.</note>
        <note xml:id="F_S_6" type="editorial"> Dryden is also the source for a musical adaption in the adverstisments.
        As a preeminent poet and quotation generator in the peroid, Dryden's name attracts the reader's attention. 
        Here, the quotation of the literary heavyweight seems to provide comedic contrast.</note>
      </div>
    </back>
  </text>

</TEI>
